In our relations with other people,
Vårt umgänge med andra består
huvudsakligen i att vi diskuterar-
we mainly discuss and evaluate
-och värderar vår nästas karaktär
och beteende.
their character and behavior.
That is why I have withdrawn
Detta har medfört att jag avstått från
praktiskt taget all så kallad samvaro.
from nearly all so-called relations.
This has made my old age
rather lonely.
Härigenom har jag blivit
en smula ensam på min ålderdom.
My life has been full of hard work,
and I am grateful.
Min livsdag har varit full av hårt
arbete och det är jag tacksam för.
It began as toil
for bread and butter
Det började som slit för brödfödan och
slutade som kärlek till en vetenskap.
and ended in a love for science.
Jag har en son som också är läkare
och bor i Lund, gift sedan många år.
I have a son, also a doctor,
who lives in Lund.
He has been married for many years.
They have no children.
Äktenskapet är barnlöst.
Min mor lever fortfarande och är
mycket vital, trots sin höga ålder.
My old mother is still alive
and is very active, in spite of her age.
Min hustru, Karin,
är död sedan många år.
My wife Karin
has been dead for many years.
Dinner is served, Professor Borg.
Thank you.
I am lucky
in having a good housekeeper.
Jag har förmånen
att äga en god hushållerska.
Perhaps I should add
that I am an old pedant,
Kanske bör jag tillfoga
att jag är en gammal pedant.
Något som varit ganska påfrestande-
which at times
has been rather trying
for myself and those around me.
My name is Isak Borg,
Jag heter Eberhard Isak Borg,
och är sjuttioåtta år gammal.
and I am 78.
Tomorrow I shall receive
an honorary degree in Lund Cathedral.
I morgon ska jag promoveras
till jubeldoktor i Lunds domkyrka.
WILD STRAWBERRIES
In the early hours of June 1st,
På efternatten den 1 juni hade jag
en egendomlig och obehaglig dröm.
I had a weird
and very unpleasant dream.
I dreamt that during
my morning walk
Jag drömde att jag under min promenad
förirrat mig till en okänd stadsdel-
I lost my way among empty streets
with ruined houses.
Ljud av hjärtslag
Ljudet tystnar tvärt
Kyrkklockor
En klocka slår
Are you ill?
Miss Agda, please prepare
some breakfast. I'm taking the car.
Gå in och lägg sig och sov,
så kommer jag med kaffe klockan nio.
and we'll leave at 10:00 as planned.
Oh, well, I'll go without breakfast.
And who will pack your tails?
Och vem ska lägga ner fracken?
Hur blir det med mig då?
- I will do it myself.
- And what about me?
Fröken Agda kan följa med i bilen
eller också kan hon ta flygmaskinen.
You can come in the car or fly.
Please yourself.
I've looked forward to seeing you get
your honorary degree.
Jag har glatt mig åt att få vara med
om när professorn promoveras.
And we had arranged
everything so nicely,
Vi har organiserat allt på bästa sätt,
och så ska professorn köra bil!
and now you're taking the car.
The ceremony isn't until 5:00.
Promotionen är inte förrän fem. Om jag
reser genast har jag 14 timmar på mig.
If I leave at once, I've got 14 hours
before the ceremony.
You'll ruin everything!
Allting blir ju förstört.
What about your son who is expecting you
at the airport in Malmo?
Vad ska professorns pojke, som väntar
på flygplatsen i Malmö, säga?
You can think up an explanation.
Om professorn tar bilen
så blir jag inte med.
Now listen, Miss Agda!
-Hör nu, fröken Agda...
-Ta han bilen och åk!
Take the car, and you'll ruin
the greatest day of my life.
-Förstör min högtidligaste dag.
-Vi är inte gifta, fröken Agda.
We're not married, Miss Agda.
I thank God for that every night.
Jag tackar Gud varje kväll
att jag inte är gift med professorn.
I've used my common sense for 74 years,
and it won't let me down now.
l 7 4 år har jag handlat
efter eget förstånd.
Is that your last word?
Yes.
Det är mitt sista ord, men för mig själv
kommer jag att säga åtskilligt-
But I shall say plenty to myself
about selfish, crabby old men
who never think of those who have
served them faithfully for 40 years.
-som tjänat trofast i fyrtio års tid.
Det är obegripligt att jag funnit mig
i frökens ohyggliga härsklystnad.
with your bossing for so long.
Just give the word,
and I'll leave tomorrow.
-Det kan vara slut i morgon dag.
-Nu åker jag bil i alla fall.
I'm going by car anyway,
and you can do as you damn well please.
Fröken Agda får göra vad fan hon vill.
Jag är fullvuxen och behöver inte finna
mig i frökens Agdas kommenderingar.
I happen to be grown-up
and needn't take orders from you.
No one can pack like you, Miss Agda.
-Ingen kan packa som fröken Agda.
-Jaså?
Really?
Old sourpuss.
-Gamla surpotta.
-Ska jag koka ett par ägg?
Shall I boil you a couple of eggs?
Yes, please, if you will be
so extremely kind.
Ja tack, det var vänligt.
Tack, snälla fröken Agda.
Jubeldoktor! Fy fan så dumt.
The faculty should have made me
honorary idiot.
Fakulteten skulle hellre
utnämna mig till jubelidiot.
Jag ska köpa nånting åt tanten
så blir hon snäll igen.
I'll calm the old girl down
with a present.
I hate resentful people.
I wouldn't hurt a fly,
let alone Miss Agda.
Jag som inte kan göra en fluga förnär.
Ännu mindre fröken Agda.
Toast?
-Ska professorn ha rostat bröd?
-Inget besvär för min skull...
No, don't trouble yourself
on my account.
What are you cross about?
-Ska hon inte ha en kopp själv?
-Nej tack.
Don't you want a cup?
Godmorgon, farbror Isak.
Well, well, why is my daughter-in-law
up at this hour?
-Vad gör min ärade sonhustru uppe?
-Ni tjoar så att väggarna skallrar.
Who can sleep when you and Aunt Agda
are making such a row?
There has been no row.
-Här är det ingen som har tjoat.
-Nej, verkligen inte.
No, not at all.
You're taking the car to Lund?
Du ska åka med bilen till Lund?
Kan jag få följa med?
Yes.
Can I come with you?
You're going home?
-Åker du hem?
-Ja, jag vill hem.
Yes, I want to go home.
Home to Evald?
-Hem till Evald?
-Du behöver inte fråga efter orsaken.
You don't need to ask why.
I would take the train
if I could afford it.
Of course you may ride with me.
-Det är klart att du får åka med.
-Jag är färdig om tio minuter.
I'll be ready in ten minutes.
Good heavens!
Ja, herregud.
Rök inte är du hygglig.
Jag kan inte fördra cigarettrök.
I forgot.
There should be a law
forbidding women to smoke.
Beautiful weather.
-Det är fint väder.
-Det är kvavt. Jag tror det blir åska.
Yes, but sultry.
- I think we'll have a thunderstorm.
- So do I.
No, give me a cigar anytime.
Tacka vet jag cigarr. Stimulans och
avkoppling. Det är en last för män.
That's stimulating and relaxing.
That's a vice for men.
And what vices may a woman have?
-Vilka laster får kvinnor hålla sig med?
-Gråta, föda barn, tala illa om andra.
Weeping, giving birth
and speaking ill of her neighbors.
How old are you really, Uncle Isak?
Why do you ask?
I know why you asked.
Jag vet varför du frågade.
Oh, well.
Don't pretend.
You don't like me. You never have.
-Du tycker inte om mig.
-Jag känner dig bara som svärfar.
I only know you
as a father-in-law.
Why are you going home?
-Varför reser du hem?
-En impuls.
On impulse. Nothing more.
Evald happens to be my son.
Evald råkar vara min son.
So he is.
-Vi är lika, vi har våra principer.
-Det behöver du inte tala om.
Evald and I are very much alike.
We have our principles.
You don't need to tell me that.
Now, this loan, for instance.
-Det här lånet till exempel...
-Han skulle betala när han blev docent.
I know exactly
what you're going to say.
Det är en hederssak att amortera
fem tusen om året och så vidare.
It's a matter of honor for him
to pay back 5,000 a year,
and so on, and so on.
A promise is a promise.
For us, it means
that we never can be free together,
Vi kan aldrig vara fria tillsammans
och din son arbetar ihjäl sig.
and that your son
works himself to death.
You have your own income.
Especially when one considers
the fact that you're filthy rich
and don't need the money.
A promise is a promise.
And I know Evald respects that.
Jag vet att Evald förstår
och respekterar mig.
Perhaps.
But he also hates you.
Men han hatar dig också.
What do you have against me?
-Vad har du emot mig egentligen?
-Ska jag svara dig uppriktigt?
Shall I be frank?
Yes, I'm asking you.
Du är en gammal egoist. Du har aldrig
lyssnat till någon annan än dig själv.
You're a selfish old man, Uncle Isak.
You're utterly ruthless
and never listen to anyone but yourself.
Men du maskerar det bra
bakom din gammelmansfiness.
But you hide it all behind
your old-world manners and charm.
Beneath your benevolent exterior,
you're as hard as nails.
Du är en benhård egoist. Sen må du
utmålas som en stor människovän.
But you can't fool us
who have seen you at close quarters.
Men vi som har sett dig på nära håll
vet vem du är.
Jag hade nån idiotisk idé om
att du skulle hjälpa Evald och mig-
Remember when
I came to you a month ago?
I had a stupid idea
that you might help Evald and me.
-så jag bad
att få bo hos dig i några veckor.
So I asked to stay with you
for a week or two.
Remember what you answered?
I said I'd be delighted.
Jag sa att du hjärtans gärna
fick bo hos mig.
Så här sa du, fast det har du väl glömtv
Perhaps you've forgotten,
but you said,
"Dra inte in mig i era äktenskapliga
kalamiteter, för dem struntar jag i."
Did I say that?
-Sa jag det?
-Så här sa du ordagrantv
- Not only that.
- Oh, no.
These were your very words:
"I have no respect
for mental suffering,
"Jag har ingen respekt
för själsliga lidanden."
so don't come lamenting to me.
If you need therapy,
you'd better see a shrink.
"Men om du behöver psykisk onani,
kan jag ordna en bra själskvackare."
Or why not a minister?
It's in fashion now."
Did I say that?
Your judgments are very categorical,
Uncle Isak.
I have liked having you
about the house.
Jag har trivts bra med
att ha dig i huset.
Like a cat.
-Som en katt då?
-Eller en människa.
A cat or a human being.
You're a fine young woman,
and I'm sorry you dislike me.
Du är en rekorderlig kvinna.
Jag beklagar att du tycker illa om mig.
- I don't dislike you.
- Really?
Jag tycker inte illa om dig.
Jag tycker synd om dig.
- I feel sorry for you.
- Sorry?
Skrattar
I'd like to tell you about a dream
I had this morning.
-Jag har stor lust att berätta en dröm.
-Jag är inte intresserad av drömmar.
Nej, naturligtvis inte.
Det är klart det.
Nynnar
Where are you going now?
-Vart ska vi nu ta vägen?
-Jag ska visa dig något.
I want to show you something.
We lived here every summer
during the first 20 years of my life.
Varje sommar de första tjugo åren
av mitt liv bodde vi här.
There were ten of us children.
Perhaps you knew that.
-Bor det folk här nu också?
-Nej, inte i sommar.
I'll go swimming, if you don't mind.
We have plenty of time.
Jag går och tar mig ett dopp
om du inte har något emot det.
Yes, by all means, do.
The place where
wild strawberries grow!
Smultronstället!
Perhaps I got a little sentimental.
Perhaps I got a little tired
and felt a bit sad.
It's not impossible that I began
to think of this and that,
Det är inte otroligt
att jag kom att tänka på ett och annat-
associated with places
where I played as a child.
-som varit förknippat med
barndomens lekplatser.
I don't know how it happened,
Jag vet inte hur det inträffade,
men dagens klara verklighet-
but the day's clear reality
dissolved into the even clearer
images of memory
that appeared before my eyes
-som steg fram för mitt öga
med styrkan av ett verkligt skeende.
with the strength
of a true stream of events.
Sara, Sara...
it's your cousin Isak.
Det är din kusin Isak.
Well, I've become quite old,
of course, so I don't look the same.
Jag har blivit lite gammal förstås,
så jag är mig inte särskilt lik.
But you, you haven't changed at all.
Men du har inte ändrat dig
det allra minsta.
Good morning, sweet cousin.
What are you doing?
-God morgon. Vad har du för dig?
-Plockar smultron ser du väl.
Picking strawberries, silly.
Can't you see?
And who shall be favored
with these delicious berries
picked in the early morn
by a lovely young woman?
Nonsense. You know quite well
that it's Uncle Aron's name day today.
Farbror Aron har namnsdag i dag.
Han får en korg med smultron.
I forgot to make a present.
So he'll get a basket
of wild strawberries instead.
I'll help you.
Sigbritt och Charlotta
har sytt en bonad-
You see, Sigbritt and Charlotta made
a tapestry and Angelica baked a cake,
and Anna has painted
a really good picture,
-Anna har målat en tavla och Kristina
och Birgitta har skrivit en sång.
and Kristina and Birgitta
wrote a song that they'll sing to him.
That's the best one.
Uncle Aron is stone-deaf.
-Vad bra - farbror Aron är stendöv.
-Han kommer att bli hemskt glad.
He'll be very pleased,
and you're stupid.
Och du har en förbålt söt nacke.
Du vet att du inte får göra så där.
- Says who?
- I say.
Besides, you're an unusually
insufferable young man
Du är en odräglig liten herre,
som tror att han är något.
who thinks he's really something.
I'm your cousin,
and you're in love with me.
Jag är din kusin
och du är förtjust i mig.
With you!
Kom hit ska jag kyssa dig.
Come and be kissed on the lips.
Håll dig i skinnet, annars talar jag om
för Isak att du försöker kyssa mig.
If you don't behave, I'll tell Isak
you're always trying to kiss me.
Little Isak! I could beat him up
with one arm.
-Honom klår jag enkelt.
-Vi är hemligt förlovade.
You know quite well that Isak and I
are secretly engaged.
Den förlovningen är så hemlig
så hela huset vet om den.
So secretly, everyone knows it.
It's not my fault that the twins
let the cat out of the bag.
När ska ni gifta er då?
When is the wedding?
I don't know which of you four brothers
is the least conceited,
Av er fyra bröder så vet jag inte
vem som är minst högfärdig-
but I think it's Isak.
-men jag tror att det är Isak.
Isak is the nicest, anyway.
And you're the most horrid, nastiest,
Du är elakast, odrägligast, dummast,
fånigast, löjligast, stroppigast!
silliest, stupidest...
I can't find the words to describe you!
Admit you've got
a weak spot for me.
And you reek of cigars.
Det är väl en manlig lukt bara?
And the twins,
who know most things,
Dessutom säger tvillingarna att du
har haft ganska fula saker för dig-
say you've been up to no good
with that Berglund girl.
-med äldsta flickan Berglund.
Hon är inte någon fin flicka.
She's not a nice girl, the twins say.
And I agree.
How pretty you are
when you blush.
You must kiss me.
I can't bear it any longer.
Now that I think of it,
I'm madly in love with you.
- You're just saying that.
- No.
And the twins say
Tvillingarna säger
att du är alldeles galen efter flickor.
that you're mad about girls.
Is that true?
Gråter
Oh, look what you've done!
Titta, alla smultronen!
And what will Isak say,
who really loves me?
Vad ska Isak säga, som är så snäll
och verkligen älskar mig!
I'm so sad!
You've hurt me so!
Vad du har gjort mig illa!
You've made
a bad woman of me.
I never want to see you again,
at least not before brunch.
Jag vill aldrig se dig mer,
åtminstone inte före frukost.
I have to hurry.
Help me pick up the strawberries.
Hjälp mig att plocka upp smultronen.
Nu har jag fått en fläck på förklädet!
Oh, and now I've got
a stain on my apron!
Någon ringer i en gonggong
Birgitta och Kristina, var är Isak?
Where's Isak?
Out fishing with Papa,
and they can't hear the gong.
Anyway, Papa said
not to wait with brunch.
Far sa förresten
att vi inte skulle vänta med maten.
Småprat
Pianomusik och sång
Plommonen!
Klappar i händerna
l Jesu namn till bords vi gå
välsigna Gud den mat vi få. Amen.
In Jesus' name
we take our seat.
Bless, O Lord,
this food we eat. Amen.
Benjamin, go and wash
your hands at once.
Benjamin går och tvättar händerna.
How old do you have to be
to learn cleanliness?
-När ska du lära dig renlighet?
-Jag har tvättat händerna.
I have.
Sigbritt räcker gröten till Angelica,
som lägger för tvillingarna.
Sigbritt, pass Angelica the porridge.
Your fingernails are filthy.
Hagbart, ge mig brödet.
Hagbart, pass the bread.
Vem har lärt dig
att bre smör på rätsidan av brödet?
Don't take so much butter.
Charlotta, the salt is lumpy.
You let it get damp.
Saltet får inte stå framme,
för det fuktar sig.
How often have I told you
not to let it sit out?
It's paint under my nails.
Who gathered
the wild strawberries for me?
- I did.
- What?
Va?
Speak up, dear.
Uncle Aron can't hear.
-Du måste tala högre, lilla vän.
-Det har jag gjort!
Att du kom ihåg farbror Arons namnsdag!
Det var sannerligen vänligt av dig.
Fancy your remembering
my name day.
How kind of you.
Couldn't Uncle have a drink
to celebrate?
-Får farbror en snaps till frukosten?
-När inte far är hemma? Aldrig!
Never when Papa is not at home.
Uncle has already had three drinks.
Farbror har redan tagit tre snapsar.
Det såg vi när vi gick till badhuset.
We saw him when we went out
to bathe at 8:00.
So you've picked berries too.
Thank you.
-Jaså, ni har också plockat smultron.
-Tvillingarna låter maten tysta mun.
Twins, speak when spoken to.
Ni gick ifrån era sängar obäddade.
Till straff får ni torka silvret.
And as you didn't make your beds,
you can dry the silver.
Tvillingarna hör vad moster Olga säger.
- Benjamin ska inte bita på naglarna.
Benjamin, don't bite your nails.
Anna, what are you doing?
Remember you're not a little girl anymore.
-Anna, vad gör du under bordet?
-Jag vill ge farbror Aron min tavla.
I want to give Uncle my picture.
-Kan vi inte få ge honom presenterna?
-Lugna dig tills efter maten.
Please, Auntie, can't we give him
our presents now?
- Where is your present?
- Under the table.
No, after we've eaten.
Det är ett avancerat konstverk
- Fritjof och Ingeborg.
A very advanced work of art:
Fritjof and Ingeborg.
You can't tell which is Fritjof!
What were Sara and Sigfrid doing
in the wild strawberry patch?
Vad hade förresten Sigfrid och Sara
för sig nere vid smultronstället?
The twins ought to be muzzled.
-Man skulle sätta munlås dem.
-Håll tyst eller gå från bordet.
The twins will be quiet
or leave the table.
No freedom of speech, eh?
Har man inte yttrandefrihet, va?
Shut up, you brats.
Sara rodnar,
Sara rodnar, Sara rodnar.
Sara's blushing! Sara's blushing!
Sigfrid rodnar han med! Haha!
Sigfrid is blushing too!
Sigfrid and Sara! Sigfrid and Sara!
Quiet, everybody!
Nu ska det vara tyst vid bordet!
But Sara!
-Men Sara då...!
-De bara ljuger!
They're lying! They're lying!
Sara snyftar
Isak är så fin, förstår du.
Isak is so fine and good,
Han är så hemskt fin
och moralisk och känslosam.
so moral and sensitive.
He wants us to read poetry
Han vill att vi ska läsa dikter
och tala om livet efter detta-
and talk about the next life
and play four-handed piano.
And he only wants to kiss
in the dark,
Han vill bara kyssas när det är mörkt
och så talar han om synden.
and he talks about sin.
He's on such a terribly high level,
Jag tror han är förfärligt högstående
och jag känner mig så usel.
and I feel so worthless.
And I am worthless...
there's no denying it.
Jag är usel, det är inget resonemang
om den saken.
But sometimes it seems to me
that I'm a lot older than Isak,
Ibland får jag för mig
att jag är mycket äldre än Isak.
if you know what I mean.
And then I think he's a child,
although we're the same age.
Då tycker jag att han är ett barn,
fast vi är jämnåriga.
Sigfrid är så fräck och spännande!
And Sigfrid is so bold and exciting,
and I want to go home.
Jag vill inte vara här hela sommaren
till ett åtlöje för er allihop.
I don't want to be here all summer
and be an object of ridicule
for the twins and all of you.
I don't want to!
I'll speak to Sigfrid.
Håller inte Sigfrid sig i skinnet, ska
jag se till att han får ferieläsning.
If he doesn't behave,
I'll make sure he's made to study
during the summer holidays.
Det ordnar far, för han tycker också
att Sigfrid är ohängd.
Papa will fix that
as easy as anything.
He too thinks Sigfrid is a
good-for-nothing and needs to work.
Poor little Isak
who's so good to me.
Stackars Isak, som är så fin mot mig.
Tänk vad allting ändå är orättvist.
How unfair everything is.
All will be well, you'll see.
Det ordnar sig, ska du se.
Nu sjunger de för farbror Aron.
Listen, now they're singing
for Uncle Aron.
Det är väl tokigt
att skriva en sång till en döv gubbe.
How silly to write a song
for a deaf old man.
How typical of the twins.
Det är typiskt tvillingarna.
Flowers nod, grasses bow
Sång
Gräsen buga
kring vår lilla nätta stuga
Around our lovely house
We our Uncle Aron celebrate
och med sång hans änne sirar
And with our song
Ornament his brow
Four cheers for Uncle Aron.
Hurrah, hurrah, hurrah, hurrah!
Hurra, hurra, hurra, hurra!
Jag springer ner
och möter Isak och morbror.
I'll run down and meet
Isak and Uncle.
You do that.
I was overwhelmed by feelings
of emptiness and sadness,
En känsla av tomhet
och sorgsenhet överföll mig-
but was soon awakened
from my reveries
-men jag väcktes
ur mina drömmerier av en flickröst-
by the voice of a young girl
asking me repeatedly about something.
-som frågade mig om något.
Is this your house?
-Är det här din kåk?
-Nej.
No, it's not.
You're lucky to be telling the truth.
Min farsa äger nämligen hela udden,
inklusive kåken.
It's my dad who owns the whole
headland, including the house.
I lived here once.
Two hundred years ago.
Jag har bott här en gång.
För tvåhundra år sen.
Oh, yeah?
Är det ditt åk som står däruppe?
Verkar antikt.
- Is that your car up at the gate?
- Yes, that's my car.
Looks antique.
-Det är antikt också - liksom ägaren.
-Du har självironi också. Fantastiskt!
Yes, it's antique, like its owner.
So you have self-irony too.
That's fantastic.
-Vart är du på väg?
-Till Lund.
Where are you going?
I mean, in which direction?
Well, I'm going to Lund.
Det passar fantastiskt.
Jag är på väg till ltalien.
But that suits me perfectly.
You see, I'm on my way to Italy.
I'm honored.
My name's Sara.
Silly name, isn't it?
-Jag heter Sara. Knasigt namn, va?
-Isak - det är också knasigt.
My name's Isak.
It's silly too.
No, unfortunately.
That was Abraham and Sara.
-Ska vi åka då?
-Jag har en annan dam med mig.
I have another lady with me.
Here she comes.
- Marianne, this is Sara.
- Hello.
Marianne, det här är Sara.
Vi får sällskap till Lund.
We're going to have company
as far as Lund.
Sara ska till ltalien,
men har lovat att åka med oss.
Sara's off to Italy, but she's promised
to ride a ways with us.
Ironic again, but it suits you.
Nu var du ironisk igen,
men det klär dig. Ska vi sticka då?
Let's be off.
Jag får lift nästan ända till ltalien.
- Det här är Anders och Viktor.
That's Anders and that's Viktor
and this is Father Isak.
-Det här är fader Isak.
-Goddag.
That peach you're gaping at
is Marianne.
Puddingen som ni står och glor på
heter Marianne.
-Det var en ovanligt stor bil.
-Vi ska nog få rum.
What a big bus.
Yes, there's room for us all.
Put your luggage in the trunk,
if you don't mind.
Fnissar
Jag måste förstås anförtro Isak
att Anders och jag kilar stadigt.
We're crazy about each other.
Viktor är med som förkläde.
Viktor's the cheaper one.
Daddy insisted.
Viktor is in love with me too.
Viktor är också kär i mig
och bevakar Anders.
It's a brilliant move of Daddy's.
Det är ett genialt drag av farsan.
Jag måste kanske förföra Viktor
för att sätta honom ur spel.
I may have to seduce Viktor
to get rid of him.
I'd better tell you I'm a virgin.
That's why I'm so cheeky.
Bäst jag upplyser Isak om
att jag är oskuld.
Så röker jag pipa.
Det är nyttigt, säger Viktor.
And I smoke a pipe.
Viktor är galen i allting
som är nyttigt.
I was once in love
with a woman called Sara.
Jag hade en ungdomskärlek
som hette Sara.
No! She was like me, wasn't she?
-Hon var lik mig förstås, va?
-Hon var ganska lik dig.
She was, actually.
What happened to her?
She married my brother Sigfrid
and had six children.
Hon blev gift med min bror Sigfrid.
Nu är hon sjuttiofem år,
en vacker liten gumma.
She's 75 now
and quite a beautiful old lady.
I can't think of anything worse
than growing old.
Jag kan inte tänka mig nåt värre
än att bli gammal.
Oh, dear,
now I have put my foot in it.
Isak skrattar
Nu sa jag bestämt nåt dumt!
Vänta, låt mig ta mina glasögon...
Hur gick det? Vi har inga ursäkter.
Det var min hustru som körde.
Are you all right?
I have no excuse.
It's all our fault.
Är ni välbehållna?
Tack och lov för det.
Mördarna bör presentera sig!
Ingenjör Ahlman.
The murderers must introduce
themselves! My name's Alman.
Min hustru har varit skådespelerska.
Det var det vi diskuterade när...
That's my wife Berit.
You can see she has been an actress.
That's the complication
we were discussing when...
Come here, Berit,
and say you're sorry.
-Kom och be om förlåtelse, Berit.
-Förlåt. Det var mitt fel.
I'm so sorry.
It was all my fault.
Jag skulle just klippa till min man.
I was just going to hit my husband
when that curve appeared.
God punishes some people at once,
eh, you Catholic?
En del straffar Gud med detsamma.
Eller vad säger du, som är katolik?
Let's get your car upright.
Vi ska få er bil på rätt köl igen.
- Oh, never mind us. Please.
- Shut up, Sten.
Håll nu käften. Somliga människor
har faktiskt oegoistiska avsikter.
Some people are unselfish,
though you don't think so.
Min hustru är lite nervös, tror jag.
Men vi har fått en chock.
My wife is a little nervous.
We've had a shock.
Just look at him measuring
his strength with the youngsters,
Titta nu hur ingenjören mäter sina
krafter med de unga gossarna.
straining his flabby muscles
to show off in front of that cute girl.
Sten, älsklingen min,
akta så du inte får hjärnblödning.
Min hustru älskar att genera mig.
Jag låter henne hållas.
My wife likes ridiculing me.
I let her.
It's psychotherapy.
Stopp!
Visslar
Jag kan aldrig skilja på om min hustru
gråter äkta eller om hon gråter teater.
I never know whether my wife
is really crying or just play acting.
Jag tror tamejfan
att det är på riktigt.
I'll be damned if it isn't real.
It happens when you catch
a glimpse of death.
-Så är det att skåda döden.
-Kan du inte hålla käften?
Can't you shut up?
Hon har stor inlevelseförmåga. I två år
inbillade hon mig att hon hade cancer-
My wife can really live a part.
For two years,
she made me think she had cancer
-och trakasserade vår omgivning med
alla upptänkliga sjukdomssymptom.
and plagued us
with every possible symptom,
even though the doctors
could find nothing wrong with her.
Hon var så övertygande så vi trodde
mer på henne än på läkarna.
Eventually we believed her
more than the doctors!
It's natural that you're upset,
Hur skulle det vara
om ni lämnade er hustru i fred?
but why not leave your wife
in peace for a while?
A woman has a right
to her tears, eh?
Kvinnornas gråt åt kvinnorna. Rör inte
vid kvinnornas tårar, ty de äro heliga.
Don't get in the way
of a woman's tears.
Gamla Berit börjar bli lite schabbig.
Därför har ni råd att försvara henne.
You are beautiful,
but old Berit's a bit past her prime.
So you can afford to defend her.
Jag tillåter mig att hysa medlidande
med er hustru - av flera skäl.
I sympathize with her.
For several reasons.
Yet you don't seem
in the least hysterical.
Ni verkar inte det minsta hysterisk.
Berit däremot är en prakthysterika.
But little Berit is.
-Vet ni vad det innebär?
-Enligt er hustru är ni ju katolik.
Do you know
what that means for me?
I gather you're a Catholic.
Quite right.
That's how I stand it.
Det är mitt sätt att härda ut.
Jag förlöjligar henne och hon mig.
We ridicule each other.
She has her hysteria.
I have my Catholicism.
So, you see,
we need each other.
Vi är beroende av varandras sällskap.
It's only egoism
that we haven't killed each other.
Det är rena egoismen
att vi inte har slagit ihjäl varandra.
Nu kom smällen. Det är sånt här
som kallas synkoper, inte sant?
There it came.
That's what is called syncopes,
isn't it?
Outhärdligt komiskt.
Very funny.
Om jag haft ett tidtagarur
skulle jag beräknat urladdningen.
If I'd had a stopwatch,
I could have timed the explosion.
Shut up! Shut up!
Håll käften!
Det kanske är höjden av sanning
och utlevelse, men vi har barn i bilen.
This may be too blunt,
but for the children's sake,
will you please get out.
För deras skull
kanske ni vill stiga ur.
Förlåt oss, om ni kan.
Forgive us, if you can.
Det var med blandade känslor
jag återsåg den här trakten.
It was with mixed feelings
I saw this region again.
Dels hade jag här min första praktik,
dels bor min mor strax i närheten.
I had my first practice here,
and my old mother lives nearby.
Goddag, goddag.
Goddag, doktorn.
Hello there, Doctor.
Jaså, doktorn är ute och åker.
Ska det vara full tank?
So you're in these parts again,
Doctor?
Shall I fill it up?
Pass me the key to the hood.
Eva! Come here a moment!
Eva! Kom hit ett slag!
It's Dr. Borg in person.
Här ser du dr Borg i egen hög person.
Han som hela bygden snackar om.
Världens bästa doktor.
Mom and Dad and the whole countryside
still talk about him.
The world's best doctor.
Vi uppkallar
den nya telningen efter doktorn.
Let's call the baby after him.
Isak Åkerman, det är inget dåligt
namn på en statsminister.
Isak Akerman... not a bad name
for a prime minister.
Suppose it's a girl.
Eva och jag gör bara pojkar.
Ska det vara olja och vatten med?
We only have boys.
-Och far mår bra, trots sin dåliga rygg?
-Det börjar bli skräpigt med gubben.
And how's your father these days?
Oh, Dad's getting a bit decrepit.
But Mom's as lively as a cricket.
And you're going to see
your mother, Doctor?
-Hon måste vara minst nittiofem.
-Nittiosex.
She's amazing.
She must be at least 95.
- Ninety-six.
- Imagine that.
Jag säger då det...
What do I owe you?
-Hur mycket blir det?
-Vi bjuder på soppan.
- This is on Eva and me!
- Absolutely not!
Såra oss inte, doktorn! Vi kan vara
lite spanska av oss vi också.
Don't insult us, Doctor.
We can do the proper thing too!
Why should you pay
for my gasoline?
-Jag uppskattar vänligheten, men...
-Det finns sånt som inte kan betalas.
There are things
that can't be paid back...
not even with gas.
-Vi glömmer ingenting i första taget.
-Fråga vem som helst i stan.
We haven't forgotten.
Ask anyone around here.
De minns vad doktorn gjorde för dem.
-Jag borde kanske ha stannat här.
-Det förstår jag inte.
Maybe I should have stayed here.
What do you mean?
-Vad sa Henrik?
-Doktorn sa att han borde stannat här.
You said you should have stayed.
Did I?
Well, thanks anyway.
Tack i alla fall.
Jag kanske ***kÅan komma och stå fadder
för den nye Akerman.
Let me know when the new son arrives,
and I'll be the godfather.
-Ni vet var jag finns.
-Ja tack.
You know where to find me.
Då sa jag till käringenv "Det är väl
ändå jag som är provinsialläkaren!"
During lunch I was in good spirits
-och berättade för ungdomarna
om mina år som provinsialläkare.
and told the young people about
my years as district medical officer.
My stories were quite a success,
and I don't think they laughed
merely out of courtesy.
Dikt till musik
Ack, när så mycket skönt i varje åder
av skapelsen och livet sig förråder.
Ah, when creation shows
so much beauty,
Hur skön då måste själva källan vara,
den evigt klara!
how radiant must be its source!
He is going to be a minister,
and Viktor a doctor.
-Anders ska bli präst och Viktor läkare.
-Vi skulle inte diskutera det.
Reciting poetry
is against our agreement
not to discuss God
or science on this trip.
Anders lyriska utbrott
är ett avsteg från det.
It was beautiful!
How can anyone today
study to become a minister!
Hur kan en modern människa bli präst?
Your rationalism is as dry as dust.
Din rationalism är ett obegripligt
andligt snusförnuft.
I say that modern man...
Jag anser att den moderna människan
ser sin meningslöshet i vitögat-
I say that...
believes only in himself
-och tror på sin biologiska död.
and his biological death.
Modern man is a figment
of your imagination.
Människan ser på sin död med skräck
och står inte ut med meningslösheten.
Man regards death with horror.
Religion for the people.
Opium for the aching limb.
Religionen åt folket.
Opium åt den värkande lemmen.
How sweet they both are!
Once you believed in Santa Claus...
now in God.
Hörru du, när du var liten trodde
du på tomten, nu tror du på Gud.
You never had any imagination!
Vad anser professorn till exempel?
Whatever I said
would be met with tolerant irony,
Ni skulle möta min åsikt
med ironi vad jag än råkade säga.
so I'll say nothing.
-Vore de inte olyckliga i så fall?
-Nej, mycket, mycket lyckliga.
I'm sure they'll be disappointed.
No, Sara. Very, very happy.
"Var är den vän
som överallt jag söker."
"Where is the friend I seek
at break of day?
"När dagen flyr..."
When night falls, when..."
"När dagen flyr jag än ej honom finner."
"Fast hjärtat brinner."
Are you religious, Professor?
Professorn är religiös, inte sant?
"Jag ser hans spår
varhelst en kraft sig röjer."
"I see His traces
wherever flowers bloom.
"En blomma doftar
och ett ax sig böjer."
His love is mingled with every air."
"Uti den suck jag drar - den luft
jag andas, hans kärlek blandas."
"Jag hör hans röst
där sommarvinden susar."
"His voice calls
in the summer wind."
Nu blev jag så där högtidlig igen.
Jag kan bli det utan vidare.
I've gone all solemn again
for no reason.
Jag ska avlägga ett besök hos min mor.
Well, I'm going to call on my mother.
I'll be back soon.
- May I come?
- Of course.
Åskmuller
Here comes the thunder.
I have just sent you a telegram
I dag på din stora dag,
och så kommer du hit.
on your great day.
And now you're here.
We all have our bright moments,
dear Mother.
Man har ju sina ljusa ögonblick,
kära mor.
Är det din hustru som står där, Isak?
Du måste be henne lämna rummet.
Is that your wife over there?
I don't want to talk to her.
-Hon har gjort oss alltför mycket ont.
-Det är Evalds hustru.
This is Evald's wife, Marianne.
-Det är min sonhustru Marianne.
-Hon kan komma fram och hälsa.
Well, let her come
and say hello to me.
Goddag, fru Borg.
Good day, Mrs. Borg.
-Varför är du ute och reser?
-Jag har varit i Stockholm.
And why are you
gadding about like this?
I have been in Stockholm for a visit.
-Varför är du inte hemma med barnet?
-Evald och jag har inga barn.
Why aren't you with Evald
and the child?
Evald and I have no children.
These young people nowadays!
I bore ten children.
Det är underligt med unga människor
nu för tiden. Själv födde jag tio barn.
Vill Marianne vara vänlig och hämta hit
den stora asken som står där borta.
Will you please hand me
that big box over there.
My mother lived in this house.
Do you remember
coming to see her, Isak?
Very well.
I asken ligger några av era leksaker.
Here are some of your toys.
I have been trying to think
which of you owned what.
Ten children,
and all dead except Isak.
Tio barn och alla är döda utom Isak.
Tjugo barnbarn.
Twenty grandchildren.
Don't get me wrong...
I'm not complaining.
Fifteen great-grandchildren
whom I have never seen.
15 barnbarnsbarn som jag aldrig sett.
I send presents
for all their birthdays.
Jag sänder brev och presenter
till 53 bemärkelsedagar om året.
I get letters of thanks,
but nobody bothers to visit me
Får vänliga tackbrev,
men ingen besöker mig-
unless they want to borrow money.
-utom då det gäller att låna pengar.
Ja, jag är naturligtvis tröttsam.
Oh, I know I'm tiresome.
-Se det inte så, snälla mor.
-Jag har ett fel till. Jag dör inte.
Don't think that, Mother.
I don't die.
Arvet faller inte ut enligt beräkningar
som gjorts upp av unga människor.
The inheritance
isn't being divided up
the way these crafty young people
had planned.
Den här dockan, den var Sigbritts.
Hon fick den när hon fyllde åtta år.
This was Sigbritt's doll.
She got it when she turned eight.
Jag har själv sytt klänningen,
men hon brydde sig inte om den-
I made the dress myself.
But she never cared for it
-så Charlotta övertog den.
Det minns jag så tydligt.
so it went to Charlotta.
She took care of it...
I remember it clearly.
Det är Sigfrid när han var tre år
och du själv när du var fem.
Sigfrid was three
and you were five.
Och så är det jag. Herregud,
så man såg ut på den tiden.
And myself.
-Kan jag få den där bilden?
-Ja, visst får du den.
May I have it?
By all means.
It's only rubbish.
Är målarboken tvillingarnas,
Annas eller Angelicas?
And here's a coloring book.
I don't know whose it was.
Ja, jag vet faktiskt inte.
They've all put their names in it.
Och Kristina har klottrat: "Mest av alla
älskar jag i alla fall pappa".
Kristina has scrawled:
"I love Papa more than
anything in the whole world."
Och Birgitta har lagt till:
"Jag ska gifta mig med pappa".
And Birgitta has put:
"I'm going to marry Papa."
Är det inte lustigt.
Jag skrattade när jag såg det.
Isn't that funny?
I laughed when I saw it.
Är det inte kallt här inne?
Jag har frusit så länge jag kan minnas.
Don't you think it's cold in here?
No, not particularly.
I have felt cold all my life.
Mostly my stomach.
I wonder why.
You have low blood pressure.
Ska vi be syster Elisabet att ordna
lite te, så kan vi sitta och språka?
Let us have some tea,
and we can sit and talk.
No, thank you, Mother.
We won't disturb you any longer.
Sigbritts äldsta pojke fyller femtio år.
Jag tänkte ge honom fars guldklocka.
Sigbritt's eldest boy
will soon be 50.
I thought of giving him
Father's gold watch.
It has no hands.
Does that matter?
Kan jag ge honom den,
fast visarna lossnat?
Jag minns
när Sigbritts pojke var nyfödd-
I remember when Sigbritt's boy
was a newborn.
-och låg i sin lilla korg i syrénbersån.
He used to lie in the lilac arbor
at the summer house.
Nu ska han bli femtio år.
Now he's turning 50.
And little cousin Sara used to
carry him around and sing to him.
Och lilla kusin Sara,
som alltid gick och bar på honom-
-som gifte sig med Sigfrid,
den slarvern.
She married Sigfrid,
that good-for-nothing.
Well, you must go now,
or you'll be late for the ceremony.
Nu måste ni gå så ni hinner med allt.
Jag är mycket tacksam över besöket.
I am very glad you came,
and I hope to see you again.
Give my love to Evald.
Good-bye.
Where are Anders and Viktor?
They started arguing about God,
and then they lost their tempers.
Till slut blev de så arga att Anders
försökte vrida Viktors arm ur led.
Ett taskigt argument för Guds existens.
and Viktor said that was
a lousy argument for God's existence.
De kunde intressera sig
för mig i stället.
I said they could talk
about me instead.
Then they told me to shut up
because I didn't understand the debate,
De sa att jag skulle hålla babblan
för det var en principdebatt.
so I left.
De skulle göra upp, eftersom de hade
sårat varandras innersta känslor.
They went up the hill to fight it out
because each insisted...
the other had hurt
his innermost feelings.
Så nu ska de slå varandra på truten.
- Where are they now?
- Up there.
Passa dig!
-Då ska jag gå och ta rätt på dem.
-Vem tycker du bäst om?
Which one do you like best?
I don't know.
Anders is going to be a minister...
Anders ska ju bli präst. Han är ganska
varm och rar, förstås. Fast prästfru...
He's a darling.
But a minister's wife...
Viktor's nice too.
In a different way.
Viktor är ju kul.
Han kommer att gå långt.
- Viktor will go far, of course.
- What do you mean?
-Hur menar Sara med det?
-En präst är ju nåt antikverat.
A doctor earns more money.
And ministers are out of date.
Though he has got nice legs
and a sweet neck.
Fast han har snygga ben, killen.
Hur kan man tro på Gud?
But how can anyone believe in God?
Nå? Fanns Gud?
Well? Does God exist?
Jag somnade, men förföljdes under
sömnen av drömmar och bilder-
I dozed off,
but was haunted by vivid
and humiliating dreams.
-som föreföll mig ytterst påtagliga
och förödmjukande.
Jag kan inte förneka
att det i dessa drömsituationer-
There was something overpowering
in these dream images
-fanns något betvingande som
borrade sig fast i mitt medvetande-
that bored relentlessly into my mind.
-med en nästan outhärdlig avsiktlighet.
Har du sett dig i spegeln, Isak?
Inte det?
Have you looked in the mirror, Isak?
Då ska jag visa dig hur du ser ut.
Then I'll show you
what you look like.
Du är en ängslig gubbe som ska dö,
men jag har hela livet framför mig.
You're a worried old man
who's soon going to die,
but I have all my life before me.
-Titta, nu blev du sårad i alla fall.
-Nej, jag blev inte sårad.
That hurt your feelings, after all.
No, it didn't hurt.
Jo, du blev sårad,
därför att du inte tål sanningen.
Yes, it hurt
because you can't bear the truth.
Jag har tagit
alldeles för mycket hänsyn.
The truth is that
I've been too considerate.
And so became unintentionally cruel.
I understand.
No, you don't understand.
We don't speak the same language.
Nej, du förstår inte!
Vi talar inte samma språk.
Look in the mirror again.
No, don't turn away.
I see.
Nu säger jagv "Jag ska gifta mig
med din bror Sigfrid."
Listen to me.
Han och jag älskar varandra
nästan som på lek.
Love is almost a game for us.
Look at your face now.
Try to smile!
-Så där ja, nu ler du.
-Det gör så ont!
There! Now you're smiling.
But it hurts so.
Du som är professor emeritus borde veta
varför det gör ont, men det vet du inte.
As professor emerit us,
you ought to know why it hurts.
But you don't know.
För trots att du vet så mycket
så vet du egentligen ingenting.
You know so much,
and you don't know anything.
Jag måste gå. Jag har lovat
att se efter Sigbritts lille pojke.
I promised to keep an eye
on Sigbritt's baby.
Fåglar
Barnet gråter
Stackars lilla barnet mitt.
Du ska sova stilla nu.
Hush, baby. Sleep.
Inte vara rädd för vinden,
för fåglarna, kajorna och måsarna.
Don't be afraid of the wind
or the birds
Inte vara rädd för vågorna från havet.
Jag är hos dig, jag håller fast dig.
or the waves of the sea.
I'm here with you,
holding you tight.
Don't be afraid, little one.
Inte vara rädd, lilla barn.
Snart är det dag igen.
It will soon be day again.
Ingen gör dig ont.
Jag är hos dig. Jag håller om dig.
No one will hurt you.
Piano
Vill ni vara snäll att komma in hit,
professor Borg.
Please come in, Professor Borg.
Varsågod och sitt.
-Har ni er tentamensbok med er?
-Javisst. Varsågod.
Have you brought
your examination book?
Tack.
Vill ni vara vänlig att bestämma
bakterieprovet i mikroskopet.
Please identify the bacterial specimen
under the microscope.
There must be something wrong.
-Det är inget fel på mikroskopet.
-Jag kan inte se nånting.
Not with the microscope.
I can't see a thing.
Please read this text.
lnke tan magrov
stak farsin los kret.
Fajne kaserte mjotron presete.
What does it mean?
I don't know.
Really?
I'm a doctor, not a linguist.
Jag är läkare. Jag är inte språkman.
På tavlan här står det
som är en läkares första plikt.
Don't you know what that is?
Let me think.
-Om jag får tänka mig för.
-Tag god tid på er.
Take your time.
En läkares första plikt...
Tänk, det har jag glömt.
A doctor's first duty...
A doctor's...
I've forgotten.
A doctor's first duty
is to ask for forgiveness.
En läkares första plikt är
att be om förlåtelse.
Javisst, ja. Nu minns jag!
-Ni är vidare skyldig till skuld.
-Skyldig till skuld?
You have been accused of guilt.
I'll make a note that you haven't
understood the charge.
Jag antecknar
att ni inte förstått anklagelsen.
-Är det graverande?
-Tyvärr, professorn.
I have a weak heart.
Jag har dåligt hjärta. Jag är gammal,
ingenjör Ahlman. Jag måste skonas.
I'm an old man.
You must be lenient with me.
It's only fair.
There's nothing about your heart
in my papers.
Det står ingenting om ert hjärta.
Do you want to stop the examination?
-Vill ni kanske avbryta tentamen?
-Nej, för guds skull.
No, for God's sake, no!
Vill ni vara vänlig att göra anamnes
och ställa diagnos på patienten.
Please diagnose the patient.
The patient is dead.
Skrattar
Patienten är ju död.
What are you writing in my book?
-Vad skriver ni i min bok?
-Min slutsats.
- My verdict.
- And that is?
That you are incompetent.
-Att ni är inkompetent.
-Inkompetent?
You are also accused of some minor
but still serious offenses.
Vidare är ni anklagad
för en del allvarliga förseelser.
Callousness, selfishness,
ruthlessness.
Your wife has made the charge.
Anklagelserna framställdes av er hustru.
Ni ska konfronteras med henne.
But my wife has been dead for years!
-Min hustru är ju död sedan många år!
-Tror ni jag skämtar?
Do you think I'm joking?
Var vänlig följ med godvilligt.
Ni har inget val, förresten. Kom nu.
Please come with me.
You have no choice.
Skratt
Skrattar
Many forget a woman
who has been dead for 30 years.
Många glömmer en kvinna
som varit död i trettio år-
Some cherish
a sweet and fading picture,
but you can recall this scene
at any time.
-men ni kan när som helst
återkalla den här scenen i ert minne.
Tuesday, May 1st, 1917.
Tisdagen den första maj 1917.
You stood on this very spot.
Ni stod här och hörde och såg vad
kvinnan och mannen sa och gjorde.
and heard and saw what that man
and woman said and did.
Nu ska jag tala om det här för Isak
och jag vet precis vad han säger:
Now I'll go home and tell Isak.
I know just what he'll say.
"Stackars lilla flicka,
vad jag tycker synd om dig."
Just as if he were God.
Precis som om han vore Gud fader.
Och då gråter jag och säger:
Then I'll weep and say,
"Do you really feel sorry for me?"
"Har du verkligen
lite medlidande med mig?"
He'll say, "Yes, very sorry."
Och han säger:
"Jag tycker oändligt synd om dig."
Then I'll weep even more
and ask him to forgive me.
He'll say,
"You mustn't beg my forgiveness.
There is nothing to forgive."
"Inte ska du be mig om förlåtelse.
Jag har ingenting att förlåta dig."
Men han menar inget med vad han säger,
för han är alldeles kall.
But he doesn't mean
a word he says
because he's cold as ice.
And suddenly he gets very tender,
Och så blir han plötsligt mycket öm.
and I scream at him that he's mad
Jag skriker att han inte är klok-
-och att man kan spy på
ett så förljuget ädelmod.
and that his hypocrisy makes me sick.
Then he says
he'll get me a sedative
Då säger han att han ska hämta lugnande
och att han förstår allt mycket bra.
and that he understands
everything quite well.
And I tell him it's his fault
that I am as I am.
Jag säger att det är hans skuld
att jag är som jag är.
And he looks sad
and says it is his fault.
Då ser han mycket sorgsen ut
och säger att det är hans skuld.
But he doesn't really care
about anything
Men han bryr sig inte om nånting,
för han är alldeles kall.
because he's so cold.
Where is she?
-Var är hon?
-Det vet ni. Hon är borta.
Gone. All are gone.
Hör ni inte så tyst det är? Allt är
ju bortopererat, professor Borg.
Removed by an operation,
Professor.
A surgical masterpiece.
No pain.
Ingenting som smärtar,
blöder eller skälver.
Nothing that bleeds or trembles.
How silent it is.
-Det är verkligen ganska tyst.
-En i sitt slag fulländad gärning.
A perfect achievement
in its way, Professor.
And the punishment?
-Och vad blir straffet?
-Det gamla vanliga, antar jag.
I don't know.
The usual, I suppose.
Loneliness.
Loneliness?
-Ensamheten?
-Just det - ensamheten.
Precisely.
Is there no mercy?
-Finns det ingen nåd?
-Fråga inte mig.
Don't ask me. I don't know.
What's this?
-Vad är det här?
-Barnen ville sträcka på benen.
The children wanted
to stretch their legs.
But it's still raining.
-Men det regnar ju fortfarande.
-De insisterade på att få hylla dig.
I told them about today
and they want to honor you.
Slept well?
Har du sovit gott?
Yes, but recently I've had
the weirdest dreams,
as if I must tell myself something
I won't listen to when I'm awake.
Det är som om jag vill säga något
som jag inte vill höra när jag är vaken.
Att jag är död. Fast jag lever.
You and Evald are very alike.
-Du och Evald är mycket lika.
-Ja, du har sagt det.
So you've said.
He said the same thing.
-Evald har sagt precis detsamma.
-Om mig? Det tror jag nog.
About me?
No. About himself.
-Nej, om sig själv.
-Han är ju bara trettioåtta år.
But he's only 38.
May I tell you about it?
Får jag berätta alltsammans för dig
eller tråkar det ut dig?
Yes, I'd be grateful.
Det var för några månader sen.
A few months ago
I wanted to talk to Evald,
Jag ville tala med Evald,
så vi tog bilen och for ner till havet.
so he drove me down to the sea.
It was raining then too.
He sat where you sit now.
Well, you've trapped me.
What do you want to say?
Nu har du mig i fällan. Vad ville du
säga mig? Något obehagligt?
Something unpleasant, of course.
-Om jag ändå inte behövde tala om det.
-Du har hittat någon annan.
I wish I didn't have to.
You have found someone else.
Don't be childish.
Var inte barnslig nu.
You tell me in funereal tones
that you must talk to me,
Här säger du att du vill tala med mig.
Vi tar bilen och far ner till havet.
and then you find it
hard to begin.
Herregud, ut med hela saken.
Håll mig för fan inte på halster.
Come on, for heaven's sake!
Don't keep me on tenterhooks!
Vad tror du jag egentligen ska berätta?
Att jag mördat? Eller förskingrat?
I almost want to laugh now.
Whatever do you think
I'm going to tell you?
That I've killed someone,
or stolen the faculty funds?
I'm going to have a baby.
Jag är med barn, Evald.
Are you sure?
-Är du säker?
-Jag fick besked på provet igår.
The doctor told me yesterday.
So that was the secret.
Det var alltså hemligheten.
En sak vill jag säga dig samtidigt.
Den här ungen ska jag ha.
I might as well tell you
that I intend to have this child.
- You've made up your mind?
- Yes, I have.
Du vet att jag inte vill ha barn.
Du får välja mellan mig och barn.
You know I don't want a child.
You'll have to choose
between me and the child.
- Poor Evald.
- Don't "poor Evald" me!
It's absurd to bring children
into this world
Det är orimligt att tro att nya stackare
ska få det bättre än vi.
and think they'll be better off
than we are.
- That's just an excuse.
- Call it what you want.
-Det där är svepskäl.
-Kalla det vad du vill.
I was an unwanted child
in a hellish marriage.
Jag var själv ett barn i ett äktenskap
som var en frisk avglans av helvetet.
Is he even sure I'm his son?
That's no excuse
for behaving like this.
Mycket rörande,
men du beter dig som en barnunge.
I must be at the hospital at 3:00.
Jag ska vara på sjukhuset klockan tre
och har inte tid att diskutera saken.
I have neither the time nor the desire
to discuss this any further.
You're a coward.
Yes.
This life sickens me.
Jag tar inte ett ansvar som tvingar mig
att existera en dag längre än jag vill.
I will not be forced to take on
a responsibility that will make me live
for one day longer than I want to.
And you know
that I mean what I say.
Jag menar allvar och det är inte någon
sorts hysteri som du trodde i början.
I know that this is wrong.
-Jag vet att det här är fel.
-Det finns inget rätt eller fel.
There's neither right nor wrong.
We act according to our needs.
-Man fungerar enligt sina behov.
-Och vad har vi för behov?
And what are they?
Yours is a hellish desire
to live and to create life.
Du har ett förbannat behov av
att vara levande, att åstadkomma liv.
And yours?
Mitt behov är att vara död
- absolut, orörligt död.
Mine is to be dead.
Stone-dead.
If you want to smoke a cigarette,
I don't mind.
Vill du röka en cigarett
så får du gärna.
Why have you told me all this?
Varför har du berättat
allt det här för mig?
Jag såg dig med din mor och greps
av en alldeles besinningslös rädsla.
I don't understand.
I thought: That's his mother.
Så här tänkte jagv Där är hans mor.
An old woman, cold as ice,
En urgammal kvinna - iskall alltigenom,
mer skrämmande än döden själv.
more forbidding than death.
And this is her son,
Där står hennes son.
Det är ljusårs avstånd mellan dem.
and there are light-years
between them.
He himself says
he's a living corpse.
Själv säger han att han är levande död.
Och så Evald som håller på
att bli lika ensam, kall och död.
And Evald is growing
just as lonely, cold and dead.
And I thought of the baby inside me.
Jag tänkte på min unge i magen.
All along the line,
there's nothing but cold and death
Så tänkte jag att det är bara kyla,
död och ensamhet hela vägen.
and loneliness.
It must end somewhere.
-Nånstans måste det ju ta slut.
-Du far ju tillbaka till Evald.
But you're going back to Evald!
To say I can't agree
to his conditions.
Jag går inte med på hans villkor.
Ingen kan ta min unge ifrån mig.
Not even the man
I love most of all.
Inte ens den som jag älskar mest
av alla människor.
Can I help you?
-Kan jag hjälpa dig?
-Ingen kan hjälpa mig.
No one can help me.
We are too old.
Things have gone too far.
Vi är för gamla, Isak.
What happened after your talk?
-Vad hände efter ert samtal i bilen?
-Jag reste ifrån honom dan därpå.
Nothing.
I left him the next day.
Hasn't he gotten in touch with you?
-Har han inte låtit höra av sig?
-Jag vill inte att vi ska få det så...
-Hur menar du?
-Stackarna som vi körde ut ur bilen.
I was just thinking of them.
It reminded me of my own marriage.
But we love each other.
Men vi älskar varandra.
Long may he live
May he live to be
a hundred years old
Sång
Jag må han leva uti hundrade år...
We heard you're celebrating
a grand occasion today.
Vi har hört att du firar en stor festdag
så vi vill hylla dig-
With these simple flowers
we want to say
-och tala om att vi är mycket imponerade
av att du har varit doktor i femtio år.
that we are very impressed
that you've been a doctor for 50 years.
We know you must be
a very wise old man
Vi förstår att du är en mycket klok
farbror som vet allt om livet-
who knows everything about life
and has learned
all the instructions by heart.
-och lärt sig
hela bruksanvisningen utantill.
Thank you.
Tack så mycket. Nu måste vi fortsätta.
Klockan är mycket redan.
Now we must go on.
It's getting late.
Kyrkklockor
So you did come.
Evald and I had given up hope.
Ni kom i alla fall.
Vi hade just slutat hoppas.
A nice drive is relaxing, isn't it?
Det är praktiskt att åka bil, inte sant?
Nu får professorn krypa i fracken.
You'll have to get
into your tails at once.
Good afternoon, Marianne.
I've told Evald you're coming.
Goddag, Marianne. Jag har förberett
Evald på hennes ankomst.
So you came after all, Miss Agda.
-Fröken Agda reste i alla fall.
-Det var min plikt.
I considered it my duty.
But my pleasure's been spoiled.
Men nöjet är förstört.
Welcome, Father.
-Goddag, far. Välkommen.
-Jag har tagit Marianne med mig.
As you see,
I've brought Marianne with me.
- Hello, Marianne.
- May I put my things upstairs?
-Kan jag gå upp med mina grejer?
-Vill far bo i gästrummet som vanligt?
The guest room as usual, Father?
Let me take your bag.
It's rather heavy.
Ni kan gå ut i köket,
så kommer jag snart.
- Did you have a good trip?
- Yes, it was pleasant.
Har ni haft en skön resa? Vad är det
för ungdomar ni har med er?
Who are those young people?
I don't know. They're nice,
and they're off to Italy.
-De ska till Italien.
-De är mycket trevliga.
- They seem nice.
- Yes, they're very nice.
Jag ville bara säga det
att klockan är en kvart över fyra.
It's a quarter past 4:00.
Jag har köpt nya skosnören.
I've bought you new shoelaces.
-Nej, jag ska åka i morgon.
-Tänker du bo på hotell?
I'm leaving tomorrow,
so don't worry.
- Are you going to a hotel?
- No, why?
Can't we share the bedroom
for one more night? Unless you object.
Nog kan vi dela sängkammare
en natt till.
-Det var trevligt att se dig.
-Detsamma.
And unexpected.
Same here.
Are we going on
to the banquet afterwards?
Nå, ska vi gå på middagen?
Yes, I'll just call Stenberg
and tell him I'll have a lady with me.
Jag ska bara ringa till Stenberg
och säga att jag har en dam med mig.
Det är bråttom, professorn!
Hurry up, Professor!
De blåser fanfar
Fader Isak! Fader Isak!
Latin
Primo pileum meum sumo
et capiti meo impono.
Isak Borg, medice peritissime
atque experimentissime-
-inventor medicorum
instrumentorum sagacissime.
Salve medicine doctor praeclarissime.
Accipe pileum libertatis
spectataeque virtutis.
Jag ertappade mig med
att mitt under ceremonien-
During the ceremony,
my thoughts strayed
to the day's events,
-i tankarna återvända
till dagens händelser.
Det var nu jag beslöt att dra mig till
minnes och nedskriva allt som hänt.
In this jumble of events,
Jag tyckte att det i denna slumpvis
hoptrasslade händelsekedja -
I seemed to discern
an extraordinary logic.
-skymtade
en högst märkvärdig kausalitet.
-Nå, var det roligt på promotionen?
-Ja tack.
Did you enjoy the ceremony?
Yes, thank you.
Är fröken Agda trött?
Ta en av mina sömntabletter.
Are you tired, Miss Agda?
I won't deny it.
Take one of my sleeping pills.
Nej tack.
Fröken Agda,
jag är ledsen för det där i morse.
Miss Agda, I am sorry
about this morning.
Are you ill, Professor?
Är professorn sjuk?
Jag vet inte, men det låter ängsligt.
I don't like the sound of it.
Är det så ovanligt att jag ångrar mig?
-Ska professorn ha karaffinen på bordet?
-Nej tack.
Do you want the carafe
on the table?
Tack i alla fall, professorn. God natt.
Thank you anyway, Professor.
Good night.
Miss Agda,
Tycker inte fröken Agda att vi som varit
så goda vänner i en hel mansålder...
as we have known each other
for so many years,
don't you think we could call
each other Agda and Isak?
-...skulle kunna säga du till varandra?
-Nej, det tycker jag verkligen inte.
No, I don't.
Why not?
-Varför inte det då?
-Har professorn borstat tänderna?
Have you brushed your teeth,
Professor?
No intimacies for me, thank you.
Jag betackar mig för alla intimiteter.
Det är bra som det är mellan oss två.
It's all right between us as it is.
-Ja, vi är gamla nu.
-Tala för sig själv.
But we are old now.
Speak for yourself.
A woman is jealous of her reputation.
En kvinna är angelägen om sitt rykte.
Vad skulle folk säga?
What would people think if we
suddenly began to say Agda and Isak?
Vad skulle folk säga?
Handlar fröken Agda alltid rätt?
They would make fun of us.
Are you always right?
Almost always.
Nästan alltid. Vid vår ålder bör man
veta hur man ska bete sig.
At our age,
we should know how to behave.
Godnatt, fröken Agda.
Good night, Professor.
I'll leave the door ajar.
Godnatt, professorn.
Jag ställer dörren på glänt.
You know where I am
if you want anything.
Professorn vet var jag finns,
om det skulle vara något.
Godnatt, godnatt.
Sång
Soliga barn av luft och ljus
Oh, jag förstår ert tysta sus
Blommande sköna dalar
hem för hjärtats ro
Hej, fader Isak. Du var fantastisk
i processionen. Nu ska vi fara vidare.
Father Isak! You were splendid
in the procession.
We were terribly proud
to know you.
-Vi har fått lift ända till Hamburg.
-Anders är alldeles nere i tanten.
- Anders is mad about her.
- Oh, be quiet.
We just wanted to say good-bye.
Good-bye. And thank you
for your company.
-Adjö med er och tack för sällskapet.
-Förstår du att det är dig jag älskar?
It's you I really love, you know.
Today, tomorrow, always.
-I dag, i morgon och alla dagar.
-Det ska jag komma ihåg.
I'll remember.
-Skynda dig på.
-Adjö, professorn.
Come on.
Adjö, Viktor och Anders.
We have to go now.
Ja, nu måste vi nog kila.
Hör av er någon gång.
-Jag tror farbror sover.
-Evald!
- I think Uncle is asleep.
- Evald!
Yes, Father?
-Är ni redan hemma?
-Marianne måste byta skor.
Are you back already?
Marianne lost the heel on a shoe.
-Ni ska gå på dansen alltså?
-Vi ska väl det.
So you're going to the dance?
I suppose so.
- How are you, Father?
- Excellent.
-Hur mår far? Hjärtat har skött sig?
-Utmärkt.
-Godnatt då, far.
-Evald...
Sleep well.
Sit down a moment.
Kom och sätt dig här ett tag.
Är det något särskilt?
Anything special?
How is it to be
between you and Marianne?
Jag ville fråga dig hur det ska bli
mellan dig och Marianne.
Forgive my asking.
-Förlåt att jag frågar.
-Jag vet ingenting.
I don't know.
It's not my business, but...
Jag har inte med saken att göra,
men blir det inte...
But wouldn't it...
I have asked her to stay with me.
-Jag har bett henne stanna.
-Bör ni inte...
Shouldn't you... I mean...
-Jag kan inte vara utan henne.
-Menar du ensam?
- I can't live without her.
- You mean alone?
Jag kan inte vara utan henne.
Det är det jag menar.
I can't live without her.
That's what I mean.
Oh, I see.
It will be as she wants.
-Det får bli som hon vill.
-Och vill hon?
And she...
She says she'll think about it.
Hon ska tänka på saken.
-Angående den där skulden...
-Du ska få dina pengar.
About that debt of yours...
That's not what I meant.
-Hur mår du?
-Mycket bra.
Fine. Just fine.
Jag tappade en klack så jag får byta.
Kan jag ha de här skorna istället?
I lost a heel.
Will these shoes do?
They're very nice.
-Tack för resesällskapet.
-Tack själv.
Thanks for coming with me.
I like you, Marianne.
-Jag tycker om dig, Marianne.
-Jag tycker om dig också, farbror Isak.
I like you too, Uncle Isak.
Då jag under dagen
varit orolig eller sorgsen-
If I have been worried
or sad during the day,
it often calms me
to recall childhood memories.
I did so on this evening too.
Isak, there are no
wild strawberries left.
Auntie wants you
to look for your papa.
Du ska leta reda på din pappa.
Vi hämtar er på andra sidan ön.
-Jag hittar varken far eller mor.
-Jag ska hjälpa dig.
I can't find either Papa or Mama.
Come, I'll help you.
Kom un